whistleblower Mark McGann disclosed more
than 124 000 documents detailing how
Uber flouted laws in countries across
Europe duped police exploited violence
against drivers and secretly lobbied
governments in order to aggressively
build its Global Empire the 52 year old
Irishman served as Uber's Chief lobbyist
for Europe the Middle East and Africa
from 2014 to 2016 and oversaw government
relations and public policy in more than
40 countries he was responsible for
courting governments in more than 40
countries to convince them that Uber was
the next big thing investment
opportunities abounded people around the
world wanted to get in on the ground
floor Executives threw themselves at the
company hoping to work for what they
thought was the next Google or Apple and
Uber presented itself as a life-changing
opportunity especially for low-income
people with access to a car they could
work for themselves as many hours a day
as they wanted this guy was the limit to
what they could accomplish but it wasn't
all that easy and the picture wasn't
really that Rosy the company began
facing pushback especially from taxi
drivers
protests erupted in Berlin London Paris
and Athens courts in Germany restricted
some of Uber's services and in Greece
the company was banned altogether
McGann was put in charge of a team that
was to confront these challenges he
argued that Uber was not anti-regulation
it was a tech company he said using data
to match Supply with demand but in
reality it was much more than that
McGann leaders said quote the Mantra
that people repeated from one office to
the other was the Mantra that came from
the top don't ask for permission just
hustle and list drivers go out do the
marketing and quickly people will wake
up and see what a great thing Uber is
unquote in reality Uber was running
roughshod over the status quo gig work
in many countries offered no benefits
long hours low pay and grinding work
conditions Uber wasn't the great job
opportunity it marketed itself to be the
opportunity that would lift people out
of poverty and to make matters worse the
company's leadership knew that from the
beginning finally earlier this summer
mark McGann provided 124 000 pages of
internal Uber documents to the Guardian
newspaper which in turn shared them with
the international Consortium of
investigative journalists and with the
most important newspapers in the Western
World the documents which cover the
period from 2013 to 2017 laid bare the
company's tactics to established
footholds and to win market share even
if that meant violating the law
and we want to bring in an Uber expert
whose knowledge of the economics of
Transport competition and regulation
allowed him to demonstrate that Uber is
incapable now or in the future of ever
earning profits his Uber analysis
through mid-2017 was incorporated into
his Transportation Law Journal article
called will the growth of uber increase
economic welfare I want to welcome
Hubert Horan welcome to the show
you're an expert on Uber and on
Transportation tell us in brief where
you think Uber stands right now as a
company in our society is it something
indispensable and that will be with us
for a long time or is it the type of
company with a business model that is
outmoded or just can't last for very
long
Uber
is phenomenally unsuccessful against any
measurable objective
criteria you can think of economic
Financial transportation
uh it's racked up 31 billion dollars in
losses it took 11 years to produce the
very first dollar of positive cash flow
no one
at Uber or following Uber can produce a
plausible Story how those massive years
of losses can suddenly be turned around
and become years of large and
sustainable profits
it's now producing less taxi service at
much higher prices than traditional
taxis did the ones that it drove out of
business before it started
um all of its claims that its stock
would be highly valuable because it
would achieve Amazon type profitable
growth in its Core Business
um which is to say Urban transport and
then profitably explained into lots of
other businesses have been proven to
have been total nonsense
uh Uber keeps claiming that oh we had
problems in the past but those were
fixed four years ago when we changed
CEOs but in those four years Uber has
done nothing to act fix its awful basic
economics are all ride sharing companies
operating on this same broken business
model
lift is concentrated in the domestic U.S
in a narrower set of markets than Uber
but it's the identical business model
yes and it it's losing money uh and has
no plausible story
um an even better example is DD in China
which actually achieved the
virtual monopoly market dominance that
Uber was trying set out to achieve 10
years ago and it still can't make money
so there's no evidence anywhere on the
planet that this kind of
business model
from Mr pure standpoint uh finances can
can produce anything
um
my research which started six seven
years ago
was was basically focused on that
question Uber's underlying business
model was always incapable of either
improving the transport service in big
cities or generating the kinds of
profits that investors needed
um it's claims about technological
advances were never demonstrated and
were always false
uh its business model is actually less
efficient and higher produces at higher
costs than the all the traditional taxi
business model did
it never had the kind of big scale and
network economies that allowed other
Venture Capital backed firms to quote
grow into profitability after initial
losses
now the old taxi industry had lots of
problems that as everyone knows but
Uber's business model didn't fix any of
them
uh Uber's business model couldn't
profitably produce lots of additional
drivers at low fares on Saturday night
when Peak demand hit or when it rained
all of Uber's early popularity and
growth was driven by billions and
billions in unsustainable investor
subsidies it's trying now those
subsidies have basically run out
and it's raised fares enormously but
there's no evidence that the mass Market
that Uber and these other companies are
pursuing will ever pay the true cost of
the service
you could be a tiny tiny Niche serving
wealthy people
um
but the mass Market that was the heart
of the Uber business model can't be
served properly
it's uh the extent that it's improved
which reduced its losses let me not say
improve profitability
it's almost entirely driven by squeezing
driver compensation has nothing to do
with scale economies or improved
efficiency it is simply cutting driver
pay what's wrong with the business model
and is there a solution they've been
producing those 31 billion in losses
over time if there was a solution
I think they would have found it by now
I think they would have found it years
ago I don't think there's a solution but
I think the evidence that they can't
produce money you know suddenly make
this service profitable is the real
demonstration
um
a niche high-priced
taxi service that is limited to the
pockets of highest demand in the city is
not a viable business they're trying to
scale back to that which again
reduces the cash drain
but doesn't make it a profitable
business if you research Uber you won't
find anyone who says oh yes here is what
Uber could do to become sustainably
profit no one has made other than just
sort of scratching their belly and and
announcing wishful thinking
no one can lay out here's how they
improve the economics here's how they
improve revenue or here's how they
improve efficiency and productivity to
make it work and again
if there was a way they would have done
it
is it only a matter of time before Uber
and these other similar companies just
collapse well the the anomaly here is
that Uber had an unprecedented level of
investor funding in its earliest years
I think it was Uber's pre-ipo funding I
might not get the remember the number
exactly right with sixteen hundred times
more funding than Amazon had before its
IPO
Amazon and Facebook and companies like
that
lost money at first but they quickly got
to becoming cash flow positive and they
funded their growth out of user Revenue
Uber was never able to do that
um
all of those subsidies
again were designed to sort of create
the impression back in 2014 and 2017. oh
Uber has found a way that no taxi
company had found in a hundred years to
to produce service way more service
higher quality service and at much lower
prices that was all false it was just
they were subsidizing all the trips they
were subsidizing drivers they were
subsidizing everything
uh they were using those subsidies to
fool investors into thinking that it had
Amazon type growth economics and oh yeah
we lost money last year but just like
Amazon notice that will will soon be you
know spouting more money than we can
count
um the subsidies eliminated competition
from all of the prior traditional taxi
operators so there was no alternative
the subsidies funded all the massive
political lobbying and PR programs that
that LED politicians to eliminate all
the industry oversight that had
protected consumers you know enforced
labor laws
um and led the mainstream media oh
Uber's the greatest thing since my
spread my friends all love it and it's
all this technology and efficiency is
really wonderful but
those subsidies the power in the early
popular meant the mainstream media never
actually investigated
and yes they've all been
proven to be complete garbage
subsequently
but no one's going back and written oh
all those stories we told you about Uber
in 2016 2018. they were totally wrong
how does Uber squeeze its drivers
um well step one
you create
a quasi Monopoly
and again think of uber and Lyft if
you're looking at the U.S situation as a
duopoly that's driven
the traditional operators out of
business so we're the only game in town
Uber aggressively lied to drivers in its
early years there were press releases
literally Uber press releases saying
Uber drivers in New York are 90 000 a
year complete dishonesty
and and all sorts of other things and
there were FTC fines for some of this
statement but uh so all of a sudden
these drivers are now
work driving for Uber go back eight
years or whatever they're getting okay
pay they're getting better pay than the
old company would do because of those
subsidies Uber's now owns the market it
simply turns around and cuts the bank
you know how much of each customer
dollar does the driver get it's been cut
back and cut back and cut back and the
drivers have absolutely no recourse
they they lied to drivers oh you'll have
total flexibility as an independent
contractor to only drive when you feel
like well no that was a lie too because
the drivers who didn't respond to the
Uber's demand for drivers when they
needed them simply got fired
you know
and and you can't operate it was always
a lie you can't operate a large-scale
transportation company or probably any
other kind of company on Purely casual
workers who show up when they feel like
that was always nonsense
um
and Uber knew throughout this that you
know
um the mainstream media
um it's wealthy users who liked it the
most
didn't care what drivers were being paid
they didn't care
that they'd been squeezed down to
minimum wage level they didn't care that
lots of them were sleeping in cars in
order to make
ends meet
and Wall Street
actually thinks those are wonderful
things that kind of transfer of wealth
from labor to Capital even if it's the
most marginal labor in an urban
Marketplace to Silicon Valley investors
that's how capitalism ought to work
they think it's wonderful so no one was
going to push back
you know whenever you know those
politicians who were being handled
buckets of cash by Uber lobbyists and
who gutted all of the protections that
had existed for decades and decades
when you know the Democratic process
somehow hell wait a minute this isn't
working we you know minimum wage doesn't
cut it let's put some basic Protections
in let's beef up
Uber's exploitation false claims about
independent contractors as you saw with
California Proposition 22 they spend
unlimited cash to beat those back
you know Uber had more lobbyists in
California than the entire banking
industry Uber had more lobbyists in
Nevada than the casino industry
this was not free markets at work this
was a Silicon Valley funded company
where the investors were looking for the
kind of riches Amazon and Facebook had
generated going to politicians with lots
of cash saying please pave the way so we
have unlimited power over workers and
consumers
thank you Hubert but don't go away we're
going to a short break and when we come
back we answer the question how vital
have Mark mcgann's Revelations been to
Hubert's work analyzing Uber's less than
transparent business practices you're
watching the whistleblowers stay tuned
[Music]
[Applause]
welcome back to the whistleblowers I'm
John kiriaku we're discussing Mark
McGann The Whistleblower who exposed
illegality at Uber we want to welcome
back our Uber expert Hubert Horan
welcome back Hubert
we're discussing Mark mcgann's
Revelations here on this program how
vital were his Revelations to your own
work the guardian series that included
mcgann's statements
were actually accurate
but they were simply reminding the
public of stuff that had been widely
reported
five six years ago
you know the magnitude and importance of
all of those lobbying all those things I
quoted you about the magnitude of
lobbying in California and Nevada that
had been in the Press at the top
um everyone knew that dozens of major
politicians had been working actively to
help Uber in return for those donations
programs like gray ball
explicitly designed to obstruct law
enforcement that had been on the front
page of the New York Giants
um open efforts to intimidate critical
journalists on its ongoing programs to
pay academic to produce totally
indefensible findings that it knew no
one would ever critique properly but it
could then incorporate into its PR
programs that had been reported years
ago
so nice to have
a reminder of all that stuff
um but
especially in the U.S it's not going to
uh overcome the magnitude of the
lobbying cash and the legal changes no
one cares
what do you know about Uber in the
developing world
its position
in those kinds
of countries is somewhat Limited
um
I'm not sure if it's how it's South
American coverage would really split out
between
the large wealthier city is the Sao
paulos and santiagos and Buenos Aires
Bogota of the world versus less
developed parts of those countries uh
stuff elsewhere they failed Uber failed
in China they failed in Russia they
failed in Southeast Asia so there are
other local companies following this
um with
probably a little more sensitivity to
the laborer and
transport issues in those things but as
I mentioned in terms of DD in China none
of them are
will Uber ever break up Urban transport
it has humongous economic problems
that's why
the New York City subway and the Denver
bus system
and
services whether it's in Mumbai or
Moscow are not private sector
businesses funded by investors hoping to
get fabulously rich
their publics their quasi-public
services
the benefits produced by Urban transport
be they expressways or transit buses and
taxis has always been a small part of
that
are fundamentally
the economics are awful
and Uber as I said Uber didn't solve any
of those problems it's Urban transport
why anyone thought
that Uber after 100 Years of every Urban
Transport Service being a public sector
operated and funded service was suddenly
a way for Silicon Valley investors to
get rich
is incomprehensible but that's what
happened
oh we have an app we have technology
technology can solve every problem known
to man and everyone in the urban
transport industry in every country in
the world in every city and everyone was
too stupid in the last hundred years to
see that if you just put it on an app
the economics will be totally
transformed
the totally stupid people
were the Uber investors who bought that
and all of the politicians and media
observers who swallowed that Hook Line
and Sinker without thinking about it if
you go back and read all the stories
about Uber's growth no one ever talked
to anyone who knew anything about Urban
transport
it was all technology stuff
technology is cool but technology cannot
and has not transformed Urban transport
into something that will spit off
returns for speculative investors
we've covered so much here any final
comments to wrap up what we've discussed
I'm I'm always asked to speculate on the
future and I hate doing that
um
if people say well what's going to
happen
one if nothing else in the world change
the investor cash could probably last
another four or five years
there is no political force
anywhere in the more developed world to
say this was a mistake we have to
restore the kind of Taxi industry we had
in 1990. we have to roll back what Uber
did there's there's no support for that
not because it's a bad idea but
politically
there's no support for that
to the extent so if everything else
there would be muddle along maybe being
cash break even and constantly trying to
shrink back
with service in cities continuing to
deteriorate prices continuing to go up
the issue for Uber is the stock price
if its investors suddenly wake up
tomorrow and said
this is never going to be worth anything
we're not going to ever become
profitable we're not going to experience
Amazon growth
and bail owns stock and I don't think
that again all these folks have drunk
enough Kool-Aid
to not be able to look think about that
critically but if you look at
the collapse of the broader Tech bubble
which is happening that's caused a lot
of people in other contexts to say oh
this technology stuff was not as
wonderful as the press releases said oh
these companies that grew fast without
any sign of profitability that was
really dumb and none of them turned into
successes no you know none since Amazon
15 20 years ago
if they're that and
pressured by higher interest rates and
an overall decline in stock the stock
market uh you no longer have massive
Federal programs basically designed to
increase stock market speculation and
inflate those kinds of bubbles if that
kind of bursts from those kinds of
external forces I think that is more
likely to be what drives changes than
anything else
Hubert Horan thank you so much for
joining us that's all we have for you
today this has been the whistleblowers
I'm John kiriaku we'll catch you next
time